not my precious
creatine multiple people have asked me
to address the rumors the Rumblings of
creatine's link to cancer and linking
this recent study showing an association
of creatine and cancer risk since
creatine a molecule produced by your
body and heavily supplemented for
physical performance and sports is
linked to so many positive health and
performance outcomes it might be
shocking to suddenly here a link to
cancer I was surprised since creatine
and I go way back I mean we even
barbecued together and watched a few
games together what a
betrayal fortunately that's not the case
here as we'll soon see creatin acts
through a few mechanisms but the first
and foremost is the effect that it has
on your cellular energy stores more
specifically it enhances our
phosphocreatine system a concentration
of Mo ules that hold on to phosphates to
donate to spent energy molecules in the
cell and regenerate them this system
bolsters our cell's ability to replenish
energy stores there's much more to it
than that but we can't get dragged into
all the cool things that creatine does
the point being this molecule creatine
is implicated in improved physical
performance mental performance and has
thousands of studies behind it in this
recent study the researchers analyzed
data collected from over 25,000 people
over 11 years in a retrospective manner
meaning they analyze the data after the
data was collected not with an
established question in mind to answer
they separated people by age and their
creatine intake and assess cancer
incidents based on if people had ever
been told they had cancer by a physician
if we put the creatine aside for a
minute and look at the age data the
vertical axis is greater cancer
incidents and the horizontal axxis is
the four buckets of age in ascending
order so the first bucket is people 20
to 36 second is 37 to 51 and third is 52
to 65 and the fourth bucket is 66 to 80
years old plainly these data clearly
indicate that we shouldn't get older
because it's associated with greater
cancer incidents so don't uh get older
that's the first takeaway very helpful I
know Superman Wolverine and Thor laugh
an immortal done what's next in fact if
we look at the incremental increase in
risk of age has on cancer remember the
more to the right the older we can see a
stepwise increase in cancer risk with
older age in the age bracket of 66 and
older the fourth bucket there the risk
is around 18 times greater Gater than
when we're in our 20s and 30s now for
context I realize that number is pretty
high but if your risk is already low
something like I don't know
0.1% which is not uncommon for people in
their 20s your risk in that fourth age
bracket would still be less than 2%
still a huge increase but a little less
uh for boating than 18 times greater
risk anyway the researchers did the same
bucket strategy for creatine consumption
the fourth bucket there is no longer the
older age but the greatest creatine
consumption the higher the bar the
greater the cancer incident still like I
alluded to at the beginning the greatest
creatine consumption was associated with
cancer risk but the association is
inverse meaning more creatine less
cancer what's interesting here is that
this seems only to be the case at the
greatest intakes I should also add
because we're looking at associations
the researchers perform some adjustments
to the data to control for a number of
factors including age sex weight blood
pressure exercise and more I'll put a
list on the screen if we zoom into
quartile 4 only focusing in on the
amounts deemed associated with reduced
cancer incidents there's a dose response
curve based on intake that dotted 1.0
line on the vertical axis indicates
normal cancer risk and if the red line
goes down there's reduced risk clearly
that's the case confirming the previous
data but these data indicate that
greater consumed levels reduce risk more
and more pretty sweet but there's some
extremely important nuances to be
addressed because as much as I'd like to
sing the Praises of creatine there's
some nuances to be understood like ever
here on physionic before we get to that
there's an extended version of this
video that you're watching it includes
data on if weight makes a difference in
these results and if creatine shows
special benefits based on age if you're
interested check out the full version of
the video along with all my study
analyses in the physionic Insiders
Linked In the description box to the
nuances first the researchers assessed
creatine intake solely on consumption
second and this is a major problem in
associative studies trying to isolate
single molecules as the causitive
variable for reduced cancer risk sure
you're controlling for all these
variables like weight exercise and so on
and that's great but it doesn't control
for any number of other molecules or
factors that correlate with creatine the
same isn't true when looking at larger
effectors like U meat as a whole or
exercise as a whole or sleep as a whole
because you're not concerned about all
the molecules and changes of a big
effector like that and you can control
for other big
effectors unfortunately when looking at
a single molecule there's any number of
other molecules that could also change
that can't be accounted for the
specificity of the analysis
unfortunately opens it up to significant
confounding something the researchers
acknowledge too oh and one more thing
notice that they didn't account for
total meat consumption nor did they
account for energy intake these are
further confounding factors so what's
the point here this is this still tells
us that creatine Associates with reduced
cancer risk starting at higher study
concentrations around 200 to 250
milligram per day which are low real
world concentrations however while I'd
love to blindly defend my beloved
creatine this Association is less
protected from confounding so other
factors driving the real effect than
other associative studies making this
encouraging data but we shouldn't make
any strong conclusions on these data
alone but heck there's plenty of
evidence that creatines amazing benefits
like those explained in these linked
videos
hey